<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Announcements | ZAN's Portfolio</title><link>https://sankethj.github.io/tags/announcements/</link><atom:link href="https://sankethj.github.io/tags/announcements/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Announcements</description><generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 18 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://sankethj.github.io/media/icon_hu_aeeeffb8443bfffd.png</url><title>Announcements</title><link>https://sankethj.github.io/tags/announcements/</link></image><item><title>Understanding the link between work addiction and burnout</title><link>https://sankethj.github.io/post/2024-10-p1/</link><pubDate>Fri, 18 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sankethj.github.io/post/2024-10-p1/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;In our recent study titled &lt;a href="https://rdcu.be/dVKtf" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Exploring the Relationship Between Work Addiction and Burnout&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, we explored the
relationship between work addiction and burnout, revealing how psychological resources can serve as a buffer against this modern challenge.
We surveyed 454 employees from 52 countries to understand how an unhealthy compulsion to work excessively contributes to burnout.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="what-is-work-addiction"&gt;What is work addiction?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Work addiction, also sometimes referred to as workaholism, is a psychological condition where a person feels an uncontrollable urge to work
excessively. It&amp;rsquo;s not just about putting in long hours or being passionate about your job, it&amp;rsquo;s when working becomes a compulsive behaviour
that dominates your life. People with work addiction often use work to cope with feelings of anxiety, stress and/or low self-esteem.
They may neglect their health, personal relationships, and hobbies because they feel they have to keep working. Even when they recognise the
negative effects of their working pattern, these individuals find it difficult to stop or reduce their work time and this working pattern
can lead to emotional exhaustion and reduce psychological wellbeing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="what-did-we-find"&gt;What did we find?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our study, we found that nearly 28% of participants displayed signs of work addiction, although fewer than 4% met the criteria for
severe addiction. Those grappling with work addiction often faced burnout, which manifests as emotional, physical, and mental exhaustion,
feelings of inadequacy, and a growing cynicism toward their jobs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, we discovered that individuals with strong psychological capital were better equipped to handle the pressures of work addiction.
Psychological capital is your positive mental strengths that help you succeed and includes things such as believing in yourself, expecting
good things, staying hopeful, and bouncing back from setbacks. This resilience significantly reduced their risk of burnout. While job
satisfaction also provided some protection, it wasn’t enough on its own for those already struggling with work addiction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we reflected on our findings, we emphasised the need to recognise work addiction as a serious issue impacting mental health in the
workplace. Although job satisfaction and personal psychological resources can help alleviate burnout, the strong link between work
addiction and burnout remains a concern. We noted that other factors, such as individual coping strategies and workplace culture,
also play crucial roles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite the protective benefits of psychological capital and job satisfaction, our research indicates that they are not a complete solution.
We believe that workplace environments significantly influence the development of burnout in those experiencing work addiction, and further
research is essential to uncover these factors and develop effective strategies for promoting wellbeing at work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, our study highlights the importance for both employers and employees to acknowledge the risks associated with work addiction
and its long-term effects on mental health. By enhancing psychological resources like hope, resilience, and self-efficacy within the workforce,
we can take proactive steps to manage work addiction and prevent burnout, fostering healthier work habits and a more sustainable work-life balance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="reference"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reference&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Towch, S. V., Atroszko, P. A., &amp;amp; Pontes, H. M. (2024). Exploring the Relationship Between Work Addiction and Burnout. &lt;em&gt;International Journal
of Mental Health and Addiction&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s11469-024-01397-8" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;https://doi.org/10.1007/s11469-024-01397-8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 style="text-align: justify;"&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stay tuned and follow me on &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://metalhead.club/@DrHalleyPontes" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Mastodon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://x.com/DrHalleyPontes" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;X (formerly Twitter)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; for real-time updates on what&amp;rsquo;s happening next!&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Understanding professional gaming, gaming disorder, and functional impairments</title><link>https://sankethj.github.io/post/2024-04-p1/</link><pubDate>Sat, 06 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sankethj.github.io/post/2024-04-p1/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;In a previous &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jpsychires.2023.06.003" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;study&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, we initiated a line of inquiry into the complex association between functional gaming-related functional impairments in individuals potentially experiencing Gaming Disorder (GD). This initial study found that the areas mostly affected by functional impairments were &lt;em&gt;‘school and/or work’&lt;/em&gt;, followed by &lt;em&gt;‘psychological health’&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;‘family’&lt;/em&gt;-related functional impairments. Interestingly, it also found that the least affected area related to &lt;em&gt;‘friends’&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following this initial investigation, we have conducted a follow-up study narrowing the scope of the analysis. In our most recent follow-up &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-024-56358-x" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;study&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; published in the journal &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.nature.com/srep/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Scientific Reports&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, we provided a glimpse on the challenges faced by Professional Gamers (PGs) compared to their Non-Professional Gamers (NPGs). We analyzed a sample of 5,198 English-speaking gamers to help us understand the prevalence of GD and associated functional impairments within these communities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The phenomenon of GD, officially recognized by the World Health Organization, refers to a pattern of gaming behavior characterized by impaired control, prioritization of gaming over other interests, and continuation or escalation of gaming despite negative consequences. Our findings revealed that PGs exhibited a significantly higher risk for GD—with prevalence rates almost double those of NPGs. This elevated risk is mirrored by an increased symptom-load and more hours spent gaming weekly among PGs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When asked if they had experienced a significant problem due to gaming, PGs reported experiencing more problems compared to NPGs. While the single most predominant area of life affected by gaming-related functional impairments reported by both groups was &lt;em&gt;‘school and/work’&lt;/em&gt;, the second most prevalent for PGs was &lt;em&gt;‘family’&lt;/em&gt; while for NPGs it was &lt;em&gt;‘physical health’&lt;/em&gt;. Interestingly, the third most predominant area of life affected among PGs was &lt;em&gt;‘physical health’&lt;/em&gt; while for NPGs it was &lt;em&gt;‘family’&lt;/em&gt;. In relation to other variables of interest examined in our study, PGs showed higher levels of functional impairments compared to NPG only in relation to overall &lt;em&gt;‘psychiatric distress’&lt;/em&gt; and severity of &lt;em&gt;‘insomnia’&lt;/em&gt; with no meaningful differences emerging in relation to &lt;em&gt;‘loneliness’&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;‘attention problems’&lt;/em&gt;, and severity of &lt;em&gt;‘headache experiences’&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The study findings support a holistic approach to GD diagnosis, considering functional impairments as a crucial factor. For clinicians and health professionals, understanding the specific areas of life affected by GD can enhance treatment efforts, ultimately improving the quality of life for those impacted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the realm of competitive esports, where the line between passion and compulsion can blur, the insights generate by our study not only contribute to our understanding of GD but also emphasize the critical role of industry-led initiatives in safeguarding the wellbeing of gamers. As we move forward, collaboration between researchers, health professionals, and industry stakeholders will be key in developing comprehensive strategies to address the challenges highlighted by this study.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let us continue this conversation and work together towards a healthier gaming community. Follow me on social media for real-time updates and discussions on the future of gaming and mental health. Together, we can navigate the challenges and opportunities presented by the digital age, ensuring that gaming remains a source of joy and innovation, not distress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 style="text-align: justify;"&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stay tuned and follow me on &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://metalhead.club/@DrHalleyPontes" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Mastodon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/@DrHalleyPontes" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; for real-time updates on what&amp;rsquo;s happening next!&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Our second gaming research project and social responsibility campaign will soon be launched!</title><link>https://sankethj.github.io/post/2023-09-p1/</link><pubDate>Thu, 21 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sankethj.github.io/post/2023-09-p1/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Hello everyone,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://esl.com/ggforall/smart-gaming" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;first successful independent research partnership with ESL Gaming&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; led by Prof. Christian Montag (University of Ulm, Germany) and I where we developed a pioneering social responsibility campaign aimed at understanding and mitigating disordered gaming harms in a large international gaming community, I am pleased to announce that our second research project and partnership with ESL Gaming will soon be launched.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Smart Gaming Project will follow the steps of our first project to allow us to further expand the knowledge we have built in the first project. As a result of the first project, we were able to publish several impactful research studies on various aspects of gaming behaviours in high-quality international journals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below I will briefly highlight my three favourite studies published out of the first project as they helped us:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.socscimed.2022.114721" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Understand how much time spent on gaming may be problematic in terms of gaming disorder&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. Specifically, we found that in a sample of 123,262 gamers from 168 countries, disordered gaming was associated with an average of weekly spent time gaming between 34.53 to 40.13 hours - depending on how gaming disorder is assessed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0261380" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Clarify the links between personality and gaming behaviours&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. In this particular study we analysed data from 50,925 gamers from 150 countries and we found that low conscientiousness and high neuroticism were strongly related to gaming disorder. We also found that personality traits were more strongly associated with gaming disorder than time spent gaming, which means that personality traits are critical to our understanding of disordered gaming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jpsychires.2023.06.003" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Shed light on the role of functional impairments in gaming disorder&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. Here, we used an initial sample of 192,260 gamers to analyse the data from those who 1) &lt;em&gt;met the diagnostic criteria for gaming disorder&lt;/em&gt; and 2) &lt;em&gt;that specified one area where gaming has negatively impacted them&lt;/em&gt;. We found that among these individuals (N = 2,162), the areas mostly affected by gaming-related functional impairments were school and/or work (50.69%), followed by psychological health (13.37%), and family-related functional impairments (12.26%). Conversely, the least affected area related to friends (4.67%). In sum, the most prominent gaming-related functional impairment experienced among disordered gamers was related to academic and/or professional activities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Needless to say that I have been extremely lucky to be involved in these studies and the project as a whole, so for that, I wish to thank my collaborators and ESL Gaming for the opportunity given to us to put research skills into good use so that we can develop knowledge able to help us understand the opportunities and pitfalls of gaming, to ultimately help those in need.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 style="text-align: justify;"&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stay tuned and follow me on &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://metalhead.club/@DrHalleyPontes" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Mastodon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/@DrHalleyPontes" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; for real-time updates on what&amp;rsquo;s happening next!&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>