<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Work Addiction | ZAN's Portfolio</title><link>https://sankethj.github.io/tags/work-addiction/</link><atom:link href="https://sankethj.github.io/tags/work-addiction/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Work Addiction</description><generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 18 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://sankethj.github.io/media/icon_hu_aeeeffb8443bfffd.png</url><title>Work Addiction</title><link>https://sankethj.github.io/tags/work-addiction/</link></image><item><title>Understanding the link between work addiction and burnout</title><link>https://sankethj.github.io/post/2024-10-p1/</link><pubDate>Fri, 18 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sankethj.github.io/post/2024-10-p1/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;In our recent study titled &lt;a href="https://rdcu.be/dVKtf" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Exploring the Relationship Between Work Addiction and Burnout&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, we explored the
relationship between work addiction and burnout, revealing how psychological resources can serve as a buffer against this modern challenge.
We surveyed 454 employees from 52 countries to understand how an unhealthy compulsion to work excessively contributes to burnout.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="what-is-work-addiction"&gt;What is work addiction?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Work addiction, also sometimes referred to as workaholism, is a psychological condition where a person feels an uncontrollable urge to work
excessively. It&amp;rsquo;s not just about putting in long hours or being passionate about your job, it&amp;rsquo;s when working becomes a compulsive behaviour
that dominates your life. People with work addiction often use work to cope with feelings of anxiety, stress and/or low self-esteem.
They may neglect their health, personal relationships, and hobbies because they feel they have to keep working. Even when they recognise the
negative effects of their working pattern, these individuals find it difficult to stop or reduce their work time and this working pattern
can lead to emotional exhaustion and reduce psychological wellbeing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="what-did-we-find"&gt;What did we find?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our study, we found that nearly 28% of participants displayed signs of work addiction, although fewer than 4% met the criteria for
severe addiction. Those grappling with work addiction often faced burnout, which manifests as emotional, physical, and mental exhaustion,
feelings of inadequacy, and a growing cynicism toward their jobs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, we discovered that individuals with strong psychological capital were better equipped to handle the pressures of work addiction.
Psychological capital is your positive mental strengths that help you succeed and includes things such as believing in yourself, expecting
good things, staying hopeful, and bouncing back from setbacks. This resilience significantly reduced their risk of burnout. While job
satisfaction also provided some protection, it wasn’t enough on its own for those already struggling with work addiction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we reflected on our findings, we emphasised the need to recognise work addiction as a serious issue impacting mental health in the
workplace. Although job satisfaction and personal psychological resources can help alleviate burnout, the strong link between work
addiction and burnout remains a concern. We noted that other factors, such as individual coping strategies and workplace culture,
also play crucial roles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite the protective benefits of psychological capital and job satisfaction, our research indicates that they are not a complete solution.
We believe that workplace environments significantly influence the development of burnout in those experiencing work addiction, and further
research is essential to uncover these factors and develop effective strategies for promoting wellbeing at work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, our study highlights the importance for both employers and employees to acknowledge the risks associated with work addiction
and its long-term effects on mental health. By enhancing psychological resources like hope, resilience, and self-efficacy within the workforce,
we can take proactive steps to manage work addiction and prevent burnout, fostering healthier work habits and a more sustainable work-life balance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="reference"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reference&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Towch, S. V., Atroszko, P. A., &amp;amp; Pontes, H. M. (2024). Exploring the Relationship Between Work Addiction and Burnout. &lt;em&gt;International Journal
of Mental Health and Addiction&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s11469-024-01397-8" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;https://doi.org/10.1007/s11469-024-01397-8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 style="text-align: justify;"&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stay tuned and follow me on &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://metalhead.club/@DrHalleyPontes" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Mastodon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://x.com/DrHalleyPontes" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;X (formerly Twitter)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; for real-time updates on what&amp;rsquo;s happening next!&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>