<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Books | ZAN's Portfolio</title><link>https://sankethj.github.io/books/</link><atom:link href="https://sankethj.github.io/books/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Books</description><generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 03 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://sankethj.github.io/media/icon_hu_aeeeffb8443bfffd.png</url><title>Books</title><link>https://sankethj.github.io/books/</link></image><item><title>Behavioral Addictions</title><link>https://sankethj.github.io/books/book-2022/</link><pubDate>Sun, 03 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sankethj.github.io/books/book-2022/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;About this book&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This book provides a holistic evidence-based perspective on conceptual, clinical, assessment, and
treatment aspects of key non-substance-based addictive disorders related to: gambling, gaming, social media,
smartphone, internet, love, sex, exercise, work, and shopping. Each chapter focuses on a different addictive
disorder and is structured in a user-friendly way to enable the reader fast navigation, yet the main aspects
of the respective disorders are covered in the necessary depth. All in all, this book offers a timely,
self-contained introduction to both key concepts and the latest scientific developments in behavioral addictions.
It addresses mental health practitioners, researchers in psychology, neuroscience and communication, and undergraduate
and postgraduate students alike.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Table of contents&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gambling Disorder (Mark D. Griffiths, Filipa Calado)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gaming Disorder (Cuneyt Evren)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Social Media Addiction (Tayana Panova, Xavier Carbonell)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Smartphone Addiction (Dmitri Rozgonjuk, Christian Montag, Jon D. Elhai)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Internet Addiction (Halley M. Pontes, Jason Satel, Almuth McDowall)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Love Addiction (Taya Bockmann, Marsal Sanches)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sex Addiction (Manpreet Dhuffar-Pottiwal)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Exercise Addiction (Attila Szabo, Krisztina Ábel)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Work Addiction (Paweł Andrzej Atroszko)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shopping Addiction (Aniko Maraz, Sebastiano Costa)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Get a copy now from&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://link.springer.com/book/10.1007/978-3-031-04772-5" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Springer Store&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/Behavioral-Addictions-Conceptual-Assessment-Approaches/dp/3031047737" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Amazon UK Store&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Behavioral-Addictions-Conceptual-Assessment-Neuroscience/dp/3031047710" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Amazon US Store&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description></item><item><title>Internet Addiction</title><link>https://sankethj.github.io/books/book-2019/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sankethj.github.io/books/book-2019/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;About this book&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This book examines how you can identify, assess, and treat Internet addiction in the most effective manner.
Internet use has become an integral part of our daily lives, but at what point does Internet use become problematic?
What are the different kinds of Internet addiction? And how can professionals best help clients? Internet addiction
refers to a range of behavioral problems, including social media addiction and Internet gaming disorder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This compact, evidence-based guide written by leading experts from the field helps disentangle the debates
and controversies around Internet addiction and outlines the current assessment and treatment methods.
The book presents a 12–15 session treatment plan for Internet and gaming addiction using the method and setting
with the best evidence: group CBT. Printable tools in the appendix help clinicians implement therapy.
This accessible book is essential reading for clinical psychologists, psychiatrists, psychotherapists,
counsellors, social workers, teachers, as well as students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Get a copy now from&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.hogrefe.com/uk/shop/internet-addiction-76323.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Hogrefe UK Store&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.hogrefe.com/eu/shop/internet-addiction-76323.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Hogrefe EU Store&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.hogrefe.com/us/shop/internet-addiction-76323.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Hogrefe US Store&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/Internet-Addiction-2018-Advances-Psychotherapy/dp/0889375011" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Amazon UK Store&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Internet-Addiction-Advances-Psychotherapy-Evidence-Based/dp/0889375011" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Amazon US Store&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;From the reviewers&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Derek Boan, MD, Psychotherapist, writing in Medical Psychotherapy Review, 26 (2), 9-10 (2019):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This book, on a topical issue, needed to be written! A well-researched, well-organized, concise book about
a complex issue that plagues societies around the world. Internet Addiction is divided into four sections:
Description, Theories and Model of Internet Addiction, Diagnosis and Treatment Indications, and Treatment.
[It] provides an overview to a blossoming worldwide problem … a foundation upon which to build, in terms of definition,
verified assessment tools, comorbidities, and treatment plans. As a bonus, after reading this book, psychologists and
other healthcare providers can earn continuing education credits by completing a multiple-choice exam through the
National Register of Health Service Psychologists, as approved by the American Psychological Association.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hilarie Cash, PhD, Chief Clinical Officer and Co-Founder of reSTART Life, PLLC, Fall City, WA –
the first residential treatment program for Internet addiction in the US:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This excellent book is a pleasure to read. It provides up-to-date coverage of the research
findings on Internet addiction, clarifies the areas needing further research, and offers valuable,
practical information on the best-studied treatment approaches. At a time when clinicians are scrambling
to learn what they can about the rapidly developing problem of Internet addiction, this book offers them
an excellent place to start.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Richard Graham, Consultant Child &amp;amp; Adolescent Psychiatrist, Technology Addiction Service,
Nightingale Hospital, London, UK; Clinical Director, Good Thinking – The London Digital Mental
Well-Being Service; Executive Board, UK Council for Child Internet Safety (UKCCIS):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the researcher, clinician, or anyone who has concerns about how the Internet is shaping our lives,
this is an essential collection of the latest research evidence and thinking on Internet addiction.
The refreshing lack of bias in consideration of our knowledge to date of this complex and controversial
problem does not shy away from the reality that for some, their Internet activities are beyond their control.
Exploring causation, assessment, therapeutic approaches, and prognosis, there is much to guide and inform
both the health practitioner and academic researcher in our unprecedented times. Excellent!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Henrietta Bowden-Jones, FRCPsych, BA(Hons), DOccMed, MD(Imperial),
Royal College of Psychiatrists Spokesperson on Behavioural Addictions, London, UK:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kuss and Pontes’ Internet Addiction provides not only a much-needed history of the evolution of
Internet disorders and their global prevalence, but also teaches clinicians how to tackle their treatment.
This is a book to include on the reading list for any mental health professionals wanting to know more about
one of the ‘new’ addictions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zsolt Demetrovics, PhD, Professor of Psychology at ELTE Eötvös Loránd University,
Budapest, Hungary; Editor-in-Chief, Journal of Behavioral Addictions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is an excellent overview of Internet addiction, one of today’s most exciting and pressing mental
health issues. The emergence of the Internet and the accompanying developments in information and communication
technology have impacted substantially on our everyday lives, bringing both new possibilities and new problems.
This book provides a comprehensive overview of research done on Internet addiction and related disorders over the
past two decades and, crucially, introduces therapeutic interventions that have been shown to work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>