<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Keynote | ZAN's Portfolio</title><link>https://sankethj.github.io/tags/keynote/</link><atom:link href="https://sankethj.github.io/tags/keynote/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Keynote</description><generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://sankethj.github.io/media/icon_hu_aeeeffb8443bfffd.png</url><title>Keynote</title><link>https://sankethj.github.io/tags/keynote/</link></image><item><title>Keynote talk on Gaming Disorder at the Universidade Católica Portuguesa in Porto (Portugal)</title><link>https://sankethj.github.io/post/2025-10-p1/</link><pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sankethj.github.io/post/2025-10-p1/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;It was a great honour to deliver a keynote talk on Gaming Disorder this month at the &lt;strong&gt;I Jornadas
&lt;a href="https://fep.porto.ucp.pt/en/about/social-responsibility/cup-university-psychology-clinic?change-language=1" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;CUP&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
event that was organised by colleagues from &lt;a href="https://www.porto.ucp.pt" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Universidade Católica Portuguesa in Porto (Portugal)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The event itself provided an excellent opportunity to speak with local psychologists (researchers and clinicians)
doing some really inspiring work in Portugal across different areas of psychology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The audience was vibrant, highly engaged, and interested on the issue of behavioural addictions. With many interesting questions
being asked!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
&lt;div class="flex justify-center "&gt;
&lt;div class="w-100" &gt;&lt;img alt="Keynote talk at UCP" srcset="
/post/2025-10-p1/ucp_hu_edff2cf0a9cfda89.webp 400w,
/post/2025-10-p1/ucp_hu_bb7f1ed94cc3dcf0.webp 760w,
/post/2025-10-p1/ucp_hu_81cc16704f5fdcc4.webp 1200w"
src="https://sankethj.github.io/post/2025-10-p1/ucp_hu_edff2cf0a9cfda89.webp"
width="760"
height="605"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is great to see that professionals in Portugal now appear to be more aware and open to the issue of gaming disorder
and behavioural addictions more broadly. This is indeed a much different reality than back in 2011 when I was conducting the
first studies in this field in Portugal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would like to thank my colleagues from Universidade Católica Portuguesa in Porto and in particular
Prof. Dr. Lurdes Veríssimo for inviting me to this important event and all other colleagues who organised the event.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 style="text-align: justify;"&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stay tuned and follow me on &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://metalhead.club/@DrHalleyPontes" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Mastodon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://x.com/DrHalleyPontes" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;X&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; for real-time updates on what&amp;rsquo;s happening next!&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Speaking at the conference organised by the National Mental Health Programme of Slovenia (Nacionalni program duševnega zdravja)</title><link>https://sankethj.github.io/post/2023-11-p1/</link><pubDate>Tue, 21 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sankethj.github.io/post/2023-11-p1/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, I have delivered a keynote talk on Gaming Disorder to an interested audience of researchers, mental health practitioners, and government officials in Slovenia in the &amp;lsquo;National Conference on the Management of Non-Chemical Addictions&amp;rsquo; (Nacionalna Konferenca Obvladovanja Nekemičnih Zasvojenosti), organised in the context of Slovenia&amp;rsquo;s pioneering National Mental Health Programme (&lt;a href="https://www.zadusevnozdravje.si" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;MIRA - Nacionalni program duševnega zdravja&lt;/a&gt;), which is supported by the National Institute of Public Health of Slovenia (&lt;a href="https://nijz.si" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Nacionalni Inštitut za javno zdravje)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a number of years now, Slovenia has been pioneering nation-wide research, prevention and treatment initiatives for behavioural addictions via its public health policies, mental health charities, and other public and private stakeholders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The conference was insightful as it provided an opportunity to discuss the issue of behavioural addictions and broader mental health with different experts from Slovenia. It is clear that public health and mental health need a multidisciplinary approach where there is transparency in the sharing of resources and information alongside an effort towards creating synergy between the different public and private organisations who are interested in nothing else but delivering mental health care to those in need.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The projects being currently developed in Slovenia are in my view leading and should serve as an example to many other countries interested in tackling the issue of behavioural addictions from an evidence-based perspective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A special thanks to Dr. Špela Selak, Mark Zmavc, Sanja Tkalec, and Tamara Arh who have all worked very hard to put up such an amazing conference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 style="text-align: justify;"&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stay tuned and follow me on &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://metalhead.club/@DrHalleyPontes" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Mastodon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/@DrHalleyPontes" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; for real-time updates on what&amp;rsquo;s happening next!&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>