<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Blog | ZAN's Portfolio</title><link>https://sankethj.github.io/post/</link><atom:link href="https://sankethj.github.io/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Blog</description><generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://sankethj.github.io/media/icon_hu_aeeeffb8443bfffd.png</url><title>Blog</title><link>https://sankethj.github.io/post/</link></image><item><title>Keynote talk on Gaming Disorder at the Universidade Católica Portuguesa in Porto (Portugal)</title><link>https://sankethj.github.io/post/2025-10-p1/</link><pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sankethj.github.io/post/2025-10-p1/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;It was a great honour to deliver a keynote talk on Gaming Disorder this month at the &lt;strong&gt;I Jornadas
&lt;a href="https://fep.porto.ucp.pt/en/about/social-responsibility/cup-university-psychology-clinic?change-language=1" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;CUP&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
event that was organised by colleagues from &lt;a href="https://www.porto.ucp.pt" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Universidade Católica Portuguesa in Porto (Portugal)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The event itself provided an excellent opportunity to speak with local psychologists (researchers and clinicians)
doing some really inspiring work in Portugal across different areas of psychology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The audience was vibrant, highly engaged, and interested on the issue of behavioural addictions. With many interesting questions
being asked!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
&lt;div class="flex justify-center "&gt;
&lt;div class="w-100" &gt;&lt;img alt="Keynote talk at UCP" srcset="
/post/2025-10-p1/ucp_hu_edff2cf0a9cfda89.webp 400w,
/post/2025-10-p1/ucp_hu_bb7f1ed94cc3dcf0.webp 760w,
/post/2025-10-p1/ucp_hu_81cc16704f5fdcc4.webp 1200w"
src="https://sankethj.github.io/post/2025-10-p1/ucp_hu_edff2cf0a9cfda89.webp"
width="760"
height="605"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is great to see that professionals in Portugal now appear to be more aware and open to the issue of gaming disorder
and behavioural addictions more broadly. This is indeed a much different reality than back in 2011 when I was conducting the
first studies in this field in Portugal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would like to thank my colleagues from Universidade Católica Portuguesa in Porto and in particular
Prof. Dr. Lurdes Veríssimo for inviting me to this important event and all other colleagues who organised the event.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 style="text-align: justify;"&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stay tuned and follow me on &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://metalhead.club/@DrHalleyPontes" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Mastodon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://x.com/DrHalleyPontes" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;X&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; for real-time updates on what&amp;rsquo;s happening next!&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Gaming, eating behaviours, and wellness</title><link>https://sankethj.github.io/post/2025-08-p1/</link><pubDate>Wed, 20 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sankethj.github.io/post/2025-08-p1/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;It is well-known that long gaming sessions can throw off daily routines and other important habits. This is why in in my latest study,
published in the scientific journal &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.eatbeh.2025.102023" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Eating Behaviors&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, I investigated how gaming connects
to what we eat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The short answer is that when gaming becomes problematic, poor diet often follows, and the strongest bridge between the two is physical wellness
according to the findings of the study.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-study-conducted"&gt;The study conducted&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This large-scale study surveyed a nationally representative sample of adults in the United Kingdom. People reported their gaming habits,
their physical and mental wellness, and how often they ate less healthy foods (e.g., sugary drinks, fried foods, and heavily processed snacks).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="what-was-found"&gt;What was found&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People with more severe levels of gaming disorder were more likely to report unhealthy eating. They also tended to report lower physical wellness,
such as less regular movement or poorer sleep routines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I tested how these pieces fit together, physical wellness explained a meaningful
part of the link between gaming disorder and unhealthy eating. In other words, as physical wellness slipped, diet quality tended to slip too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mental wellness did relate to gaming disorder, but it did not explain the connection to unhealthy eating in this study. Perhaps focusing
only on mood or general psychological well-being may miss an important part of the picture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="practical-implications"&gt;Practical implications&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are trying to reduce the health downsides of problematic gaming, start with the body. Rebuilding daily routines around movement,
sleep, and simple meal planning could be a practical way to weaken the pull toward less healthy foods (e.g., fast food).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This does not mean mental health
is unimportant, only that physical wellness may be the most direct lever for improving diet when gaming has become problematic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="what-to-keep-in-mind"&gt;What to keep in mind&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The results come from a single-time survey, so we cannot say what causes what. People also reported their own habits, which can be imperfect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mental wellness measure used in the study was broad, so it may have missed specific pieces of the puzzle such as emotion regulation or stress
management that could still matter even if the overall score did not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="takeaway"&gt;Takeaway&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Problematic gaming and poor diet often travel together. In this study, the clearest link ran through everyday physical wellness, implying that
strengthening routines for sleep, movement, and basic food choices may be a straightforward way to improve diet while addressing gaming problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="reference"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reference&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pontes, H. M. (2025). From high scores to high calories: Investigating the relationship between gaming disorder and unhealthy eating behaviors
in the context of wellness. &lt;em&gt;Eating Behaviors&lt;/em&gt;, 102023. &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.eatbeh.2025.102023" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.eatbeh.2025.102023&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 style="text-align: justify;"&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stay tuned and follow me on &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://metalhead.club/@DrHalleyPontes" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Mastodon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://x.com/DrHalleyPontes" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;X&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; for real-time updates on what&amp;rsquo;s happening next!&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Assessing Internet Gaming Disorder - insights from our latest research</title><link>https://sankethj.github.io/post/2024-10-p2/</link><pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sankethj.github.io/post/2024-10-p2/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;In recent years, the conversation around Gaming Disorder has gained significant traction, especially as more people recognise
the impact of excessive gaming on mental health. In our &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.abrep.2024.100567" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;latest study&lt;/a&gt;, we took a closer look at two of the most widely used assessment
tools for GD: the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chb.2014.12.006" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Internet Gaming Disorder Scale–Short-Form (IGDS9-SF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; and
the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s11469-019-00088-z" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Gaming Disorder Test (GDT)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. Our goal was to evaluate how well these tools measure
disordered gaming and what that means for individuals and clinicians alike.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="what-is-gaming-disorder"&gt;What is Gaming Disorder?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.who.int/standards/classifications/frequently-asked-questions/gaming-disorder" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Gaming Disorder&lt;/a&gt; is a condition recognized in
the World Health Organisation&amp;rsquo;s International Classification of Diseases (ICD-11).
It involves a pattern of gaming behaviour where a person struggles to control their gaming habits, prioritises gaming over other
important activities and interests, and continues to play even when it leads to negative effects in their life.
Essentially, it means that gaming becomes more important than other aspects of daily living, which can harm a person&amp;rsquo;s wellbeing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="about-our-study"&gt;About our study&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For this study, we gathered a diverse group of 605 participants, all of whom were Spanish-speaking individuals aged between 16 and 73 years
who played video games at least once a week. Through an online survey, we assessed the reliability and effectiveness of the IGDS9-SF and GDT
in identifying symptoms of disordered gaming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using advanced statistical methods, we analysed the data to determine whether these two scales accurately measure a single underlying trait
(i.e., disordered gaming) and how well they can distinguish between different levels of severity. Accurately measuring Gaming Disorder is
crucial for identifying and treating individuals who may be struggling with excessive gaming and understanding the severity of their issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="our-key-findings"&gt;Our key findings&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of our most significant findings was that both the IGDS9-SF and GDT are unidimensional. This means that each scale effectively measures
one core aspect of Gaming Disorder. The results showed that the items (which represent the unique symptoms of Gaming Disorder) on both scales
work well together to reflect the same underlying issue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, both scales demonstrated high reliability, which means that they consistently provide accurate measurements of Gaming Disorder symptoms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also explored how well the items of each scale can differentiate between varying levels of Gaming Disorder. We found that the GDT performed
particularly well, achieving a strong scalability coefficient, which suggests that its items are effective at distinguishing between
individuals with different levels of gaming issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also found a clear hierarchy of item difficulty within both scales. For instance, in the IGDS9-SF, the most challenging item related
to the experience of &lt;strong&gt;negative consequences of gaming&lt;/strong&gt;, while the easiest item was about &lt;strong&gt;escapism&lt;/strong&gt;, which means that when assessing
Gaming Disorder, it is important to understand that the potential negative consequences resulting from excessive gaming is a much better
indicator of Gaming Disorder than playing video games excessively to escape real-life problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the GDT, the most difficult item involved &lt;strong&gt;experiencing significant life problems&lt;/strong&gt; due to gaming, which is highly consistent with the
findings of the IGDS9-SF. Interestingly, the easiest item was related to giving &lt;strong&gt;increased priority to gaming&lt;/strong&gt;, which is an important sign
of Gaming Disorder but certainly not as critical compared to the detrimental consequences excessive gaming can cause.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also found that &lt;strong&gt;withdrawal symptoms&lt;/strong&gt; (in IGDS9-SF) and &lt;strong&gt;experience of significant problems in life&lt;/strong&gt; (in GDT) were the most discriminative
items. This finding suggests that these two symptoms are particularly effective in differentiating individuals experiencing Gaming Disorder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="implications-of-our-findings"&gt;Implications of our findings&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The implications of our study are important for both individuals and mental health professionals. Firstly, it is important to pay attention
to more critical symptoms as these may require a greater level of intervention. One of the critical symptoms we identified relates to the
negative impact of excessive gaming on a person&amp;rsquo;s life (e.g., missing real-life opportunities, skipping school, missing work, etc).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secondly, the most discriminative items were: &lt;strong&gt;withdrawal symptoms&lt;/strong&gt; in the IGDS9-SF and the &lt;strong&gt;experience of significant life problems&lt;/strong&gt; in
the GDT. These two symptoms should be prioritised during assessments and clinicians should pay close attention to them as they appear to indicate
a more severe form of Gaming Disorder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, our findings suggest that the GDT may be slightly more effective than the IGDS9-SF in distinguishing between individuals with high
and low levels of Gaming Disorder, a finding that can help guide health practitioners in selecting the most appropriate assessment tool for their
clinical work with clients struggling with Gaming Disorder, ultimately leading to better targeted interventions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, our study supports the psychometric robustness of both the IGDS9-SF and GDT, confirming their utility in both research and
clinical settings for assessing Gaming Disorder. By utilising these tools, researchers and clinicians can better identify individuals at
risk for Gaming Disorder and implement more focussed interventions aimed at treating this condition and promoting healthier gaming behaviours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the conversation around gaming and mental health continues to evolve, our findings contribute to a growing body of evidence that can help
shape effective strategies for prevention and intervention in the realm of Gaming Disorder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="reference"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reference&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maldonado-Murciano, L., Pontes, H. M., Barrios, M., Gómez-Benito, J., &amp;amp; Guilera, G. (2024). Mokken scale analysis of the Internet Gaming Disorder
Scale–Short-Form and the Gaming Disorder Test. &lt;em&gt;Addictive Behaviors Reports&lt;/em&gt;, 100567. &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.abrep.2024.100567" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.abrep.2024.100567&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 style="text-align: justify;"&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stay tuned and follow me on &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://metalhead.club/@DrHalleyPontes" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Mastodon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://x.com/DrHalleyPontes" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;X (formerly Twitter)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; for real-time updates on what&amp;rsquo;s happening next!&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Understanding the link between work addiction and burnout</title><link>https://sankethj.github.io/post/2024-10-p1/</link><pubDate>Fri, 18 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sankethj.github.io/post/2024-10-p1/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;In our recent study titled &lt;a href="https://rdcu.be/dVKtf" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Exploring the Relationship Between Work Addiction and Burnout&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, we explored the
relationship between work addiction and burnout, revealing how psychological resources can serve as a buffer against this modern challenge.
We surveyed 454 employees from 52 countries to understand how an unhealthy compulsion to work excessively contributes to burnout.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="what-is-work-addiction"&gt;What is work addiction?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Work addiction, also sometimes referred to as workaholism, is a psychological condition where a person feels an uncontrollable urge to work
excessively. It&amp;rsquo;s not just about putting in long hours or being passionate about your job, it&amp;rsquo;s when working becomes a compulsive behaviour
that dominates your life. People with work addiction often use work to cope with feelings of anxiety, stress and/or low self-esteem.
They may neglect their health, personal relationships, and hobbies because they feel they have to keep working. Even when they recognise the
negative effects of their working pattern, these individuals find it difficult to stop or reduce their work time and this working pattern
can lead to emotional exhaustion and reduce psychological wellbeing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="what-did-we-find"&gt;What did we find?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our study, we found that nearly 28% of participants displayed signs of work addiction, although fewer than 4% met the criteria for
severe addiction. Those grappling with work addiction often faced burnout, which manifests as emotional, physical, and mental exhaustion,
feelings of inadequacy, and a growing cynicism toward their jobs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, we discovered that individuals with strong psychological capital were better equipped to handle the pressures of work addiction.
Psychological capital is your positive mental strengths that help you succeed and includes things such as believing in yourself, expecting
good things, staying hopeful, and bouncing back from setbacks. This resilience significantly reduced their risk of burnout. While job
satisfaction also provided some protection, it wasn’t enough on its own for those already struggling with work addiction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we reflected on our findings, we emphasised the need to recognise work addiction as a serious issue impacting mental health in the
workplace. Although job satisfaction and personal psychological resources can help alleviate burnout, the strong link between work
addiction and burnout remains a concern. We noted that other factors, such as individual coping strategies and workplace culture,
also play crucial roles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite the protective benefits of psychological capital and job satisfaction, our research indicates that they are not a complete solution.
We believe that workplace environments significantly influence the development of burnout in those experiencing work addiction, and further
research is essential to uncover these factors and develop effective strategies for promoting wellbeing at work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, our study highlights the importance for both employers and employees to acknowledge the risks associated with work addiction
and its long-term effects on mental health. By enhancing psychological resources like hope, resilience, and self-efficacy within the workforce,
we can take proactive steps to manage work addiction and prevent burnout, fostering healthier work habits and a more sustainable work-life balance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="reference"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reference&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Towch, S. V., Atroszko, P. A., &amp;amp; Pontes, H. M. (2024). Exploring the Relationship Between Work Addiction and Burnout. &lt;em&gt;International Journal
of Mental Health and Addiction&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s11469-024-01397-8" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;https://doi.org/10.1007/s11469-024-01397-8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 style="text-align: justify;"&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stay tuned and follow me on &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://metalhead.club/@DrHalleyPontes" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Mastodon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://x.com/DrHalleyPontes" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;X (formerly Twitter)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; for real-time updates on what&amp;rsquo;s happening next!&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Understanding professional gaming, gaming disorder, and functional impairments</title><link>https://sankethj.github.io/post/2024-04-p1/</link><pubDate>Sat, 06 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sankethj.github.io/post/2024-04-p1/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;In a previous &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jpsychires.2023.06.003" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;study&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, we initiated a line of inquiry into the complex association between functional gaming-related functional impairments in individuals potentially experiencing Gaming Disorder (GD). This initial study found that the areas mostly affected by functional impairments were &lt;em&gt;‘school and/or work’&lt;/em&gt;, followed by &lt;em&gt;‘psychological health’&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;‘family’&lt;/em&gt;-related functional impairments. Interestingly, it also found that the least affected area related to &lt;em&gt;‘friends’&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following this initial investigation, we have conducted a follow-up study narrowing the scope of the analysis. In our most recent follow-up &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-024-56358-x" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;study&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; published in the journal &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.nature.com/srep/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Scientific Reports&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, we provided a glimpse on the challenges faced by Professional Gamers (PGs) compared to their Non-Professional Gamers (NPGs). We analyzed a sample of 5,198 English-speaking gamers to help us understand the prevalence of GD and associated functional impairments within these communities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The phenomenon of GD, officially recognized by the World Health Organization, refers to a pattern of gaming behavior characterized by impaired control, prioritization of gaming over other interests, and continuation or escalation of gaming despite negative consequences. Our findings revealed that PGs exhibited a significantly higher risk for GD—with prevalence rates almost double those of NPGs. This elevated risk is mirrored by an increased symptom-load and more hours spent gaming weekly among PGs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When asked if they had experienced a significant problem due to gaming, PGs reported experiencing more problems compared to NPGs. While the single most predominant area of life affected by gaming-related functional impairments reported by both groups was &lt;em&gt;‘school and/work’&lt;/em&gt;, the second most prevalent for PGs was &lt;em&gt;‘family’&lt;/em&gt; while for NPGs it was &lt;em&gt;‘physical health’&lt;/em&gt;. Interestingly, the third most predominant area of life affected among PGs was &lt;em&gt;‘physical health’&lt;/em&gt; while for NPGs it was &lt;em&gt;‘family’&lt;/em&gt;. In relation to other variables of interest examined in our study, PGs showed higher levels of functional impairments compared to NPG only in relation to overall &lt;em&gt;‘psychiatric distress’&lt;/em&gt; and severity of &lt;em&gt;‘insomnia’&lt;/em&gt; with no meaningful differences emerging in relation to &lt;em&gt;‘loneliness’&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;‘attention problems’&lt;/em&gt;, and severity of &lt;em&gt;‘headache experiences’&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The study findings support a holistic approach to GD diagnosis, considering functional impairments as a crucial factor. For clinicians and health professionals, understanding the specific areas of life affected by GD can enhance treatment efforts, ultimately improving the quality of life for those impacted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the realm of competitive esports, where the line between passion and compulsion can blur, the insights generate by our study not only contribute to our understanding of GD but also emphasize the critical role of industry-led initiatives in safeguarding the wellbeing of gamers. As we move forward, collaboration between researchers, health professionals, and industry stakeholders will be key in developing comprehensive strategies to address the challenges highlighted by this study.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let us continue this conversation and work together towards a healthier gaming community. Follow me on social media for real-time updates and discussions on the future of gaming and mental health. Together, we can navigate the challenges and opportunities presented by the digital age, ensuring that gaming remains a source of joy and innovation, not distress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 style="text-align: justify;"&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stay tuned and follow me on &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://metalhead.club/@DrHalleyPontes" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Mastodon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/@DrHalleyPontes" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; for real-time updates on what&amp;rsquo;s happening next!&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Speaking at the conference organised by the National Mental Health Programme of Slovenia (Nacionalni program duševnega zdravja)</title><link>https://sankethj.github.io/post/2023-11-p1/</link><pubDate>Tue, 21 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sankethj.github.io/post/2023-11-p1/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, I have delivered a keynote talk on Gaming Disorder to an interested audience of researchers, mental health practitioners, and government officials in Slovenia in the &amp;lsquo;National Conference on the Management of Non-Chemical Addictions&amp;rsquo; (Nacionalna Konferenca Obvladovanja Nekemičnih Zasvojenosti), organised in the context of Slovenia&amp;rsquo;s pioneering National Mental Health Programme (&lt;a href="https://www.zadusevnozdravje.si" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;MIRA - Nacionalni program duševnega zdravja&lt;/a&gt;), which is supported by the National Institute of Public Health of Slovenia (&lt;a href="https://nijz.si" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Nacionalni Inštitut za javno zdravje)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a number of years now, Slovenia has been pioneering nation-wide research, prevention and treatment initiatives for behavioural addictions via its public health policies, mental health charities, and other public and private stakeholders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The conference was insightful as it provided an opportunity to discuss the issue of behavioural addictions and broader mental health with different experts from Slovenia. It is clear that public health and mental health need a multidisciplinary approach where there is transparency in the sharing of resources and information alongside an effort towards creating synergy between the different public and private organisations who are interested in nothing else but delivering mental health care to those in need.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The projects being currently developed in Slovenia are in my view leading and should serve as an example to many other countries interested in tackling the issue of behavioural addictions from an evidence-based perspective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A special thanks to Dr. Špela Selak, Mark Zmavc, Sanja Tkalec, and Tamara Arh who have all worked very hard to put up such an amazing conference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 style="text-align: justify;"&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stay tuned and follow me on &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://metalhead.club/@DrHalleyPontes" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Mastodon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/@DrHalleyPontes" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; for real-time updates on what&amp;rsquo;s happening next!&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Our second gaming research project and social responsibility campaign will soon be launched!</title><link>https://sankethj.github.io/post/2023-09-p1/</link><pubDate>Thu, 21 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sankethj.github.io/post/2023-09-p1/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Hello everyone,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://esl.com/ggforall/smart-gaming" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;first successful independent research partnership with ESL Gaming&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; led by Prof. Christian Montag (University of Ulm, Germany) and I where we developed a pioneering social responsibility campaign aimed at understanding and mitigating disordered gaming harms in a large international gaming community, I am pleased to announce that our second research project and partnership with ESL Gaming will soon be launched.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Smart Gaming Project will follow the steps of our first project to allow us to further expand the knowledge we have built in the first project. As a result of the first project, we were able to publish several impactful research studies on various aspects of gaming behaviours in high-quality international journals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below I will briefly highlight my three favourite studies published out of the first project as they helped us:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.socscimed.2022.114721" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Understand how much time spent on gaming may be problematic in terms of gaming disorder&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. Specifically, we found that in a sample of 123,262 gamers from 168 countries, disordered gaming was associated with an average of weekly spent time gaming between 34.53 to 40.13 hours - depending on how gaming disorder is assessed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0261380" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Clarify the links between personality and gaming behaviours&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. In this particular study we analysed data from 50,925 gamers from 150 countries and we found that low conscientiousness and high neuroticism were strongly related to gaming disorder. We also found that personality traits were more strongly associated with gaming disorder than time spent gaming, which means that personality traits are critical to our understanding of disordered gaming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jpsychires.2023.06.003" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Shed light on the role of functional impairments in gaming disorder&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. Here, we used an initial sample of 192,260 gamers to analyse the data from those who 1) &lt;em&gt;met the diagnostic criteria for gaming disorder&lt;/em&gt; and 2) &lt;em&gt;that specified one area where gaming has negatively impacted them&lt;/em&gt;. We found that among these individuals (N = 2,162), the areas mostly affected by gaming-related functional impairments were school and/or work (50.69%), followed by psychological health (13.37%), and family-related functional impairments (12.26%). Conversely, the least affected area related to friends (4.67%). In sum, the most prominent gaming-related functional impairment experienced among disordered gamers was related to academic and/or professional activities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Needless to say that I have been extremely lucky to be involved in these studies and the project as a whole, so for that, I wish to thank my collaborators and ESL Gaming for the opportunity given to us to put research skills into good use so that we can develop knowledge able to help us understand the opportunities and pitfalls of gaming, to ultimately help those in need.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 style="text-align: justify;"&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stay tuned and follow me on &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://metalhead.club/@DrHalleyPontes" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Mastodon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/@DrHalleyPontes" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; for real-time updates on what&amp;rsquo;s happening next!&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Assessment of Gaming Disorder with the IGDS9-SF</title><link>https://sankethj.github.io/post/2022-12-p2/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sankethj.github.io/post/2022-12-p2/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Hello everyone,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was pleased to see that a recent study published by Anthony and colleagues (2022) in the journal &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1037/cps0000123" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Clinical Psychology: Science and Practice&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; provided further insights on the psychometric properties and usability of the &lt;strong&gt;Internet Disorder Scale-Short Form (IDS9-SF)&lt;/strong&gt;, which was the first brief standardized assessment tool for &amp;lsquo;Internet Gaming Disorder&amp;rsquo; as defined in the DSM-5.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The IGDS9-SF was published in December 2014 in the journal &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chb.2014.12.006" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Computers in Human Behavior&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, and after nearly a decade since its publication and numerous studies supporting its use worldwide, a new study provided further support to previous research.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Upon evaluating a set of 22 psychometric tests measuring &amp;lsquo;Internet Gaming Disorder&amp;rsquo;, Anthony and colleagues (2022) reported that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote style="text-align: justify;"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Among all reviewed measures, the IGDS9-SF has been evaluated by the highest number of empirical studies (n = 26). In contrast, all other measures were evaluated by only a few studies (ns = 1–5).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They further noted that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote style="text-align: justify;"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Based on the COSMIN guideline, the IGDS9-SF demonstrates sound structural validity, internal consistency reliability, construct validity (convergent and divergent validities), test-retest reliability, and measurement invariance among gender, age groups (including three studies evaluating measurement invariance between adolescent and adult samples), and regions with moderate- to high methodological quality.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Find out more about the IGDS9-SF and available documentation &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.halleypontes.com/tests/ids9-sf/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stay tuned and follow me on &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://metalhead.club/@DrHalleyPontes" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Mastodon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; for real-time updates on what&amp;rsquo;s happening!&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Welcome to my new website!</title><link>https://sankethj.github.io/post/2022-12-p1/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sankethj.github.io/post/2022-12-p1/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Welcome aboard!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am really excited to release the new version of my website, which was developed using &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.r-project.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;R&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://gohugo.io/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Hugo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope we can keep connected and that I have enough time to keep you posted about my work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the meantime, I wish you all a truly awesome happy new year!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stay tuned and follow me on &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://metalhead.club/@DrHalleyPontes" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Mastodon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; for real-time updates on what&amp;rsquo;s happening!&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>