<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Blog | Dr. Halley Pontes</title>
    <link>http://localhost:4321/en/post/</link>
      <atom:link href="http://localhost:4321/en/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 06 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>http://localhost:4321/media/icon_hu7729264130191091259.png</url>
      <title>Blog</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/en/post/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Understanding professional gaming, gaming disorder, and functional impairments</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/en/post/2024-04-p1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/en/post/2024-04-p1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In a previous &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jpsychires.2023.06.003&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;study&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, we initiated a line of inquiry into the complex association between functional gaming-related functional impairments in individuals potentially experiencing Gaming Disorder (GD). This initial study found that the areas mostly affected by functional impairments were &lt;em&gt;‘school and/or work’&lt;/em&gt;, followed by &lt;em&gt;‘psychological health’&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;‘family’&lt;/em&gt;-related functional impairments. Interestingly, it also found that the least affected area related to &lt;em&gt;‘friends’&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following this initial investigation, we have conducted a follow-up study narrowing the scope of the analysis. In our most recent follow-up &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-024-56358-x&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;study&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; published in the journal &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/srep/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Scientific Reports&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, we provided a glimpse on the challenges faced by Professional Gamers (PGs) compared to their Non-Professional Gamers (NPGs). We analyzed a sample of 5,198 English-speaking gamers to help us understand the prevalence of GD and associated functional impairments within these communities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The phenomenon of GD, officially recognized by the World Health Organization, refers to a pattern of gaming behavior characterized by impaired control, prioritization of gaming over other interests, and continuation or escalation of gaming despite negative consequences. Our findings revealed that PGs exhibited a significantly higher risk for GD—with prevalence rates almost double those of NPGs. This elevated risk is mirrored by an increased symptom-load and more hours spent gaming weekly among PGs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When asked if they had experienced a significant problem due to gaming, PGs reported experiencing more problems compared to NPGs. While the single most predominant area of life affected by gaming-related functional impairments reported by both groups was &lt;em&gt;‘school and/work’&lt;/em&gt;, the second most prevalent for PGs was &lt;em&gt;‘family’&lt;/em&gt; while for NPGs it was &lt;em&gt;‘physical health’&lt;/em&gt;. Interestingly, the third most predominant area of life affected among PGs was &lt;em&gt;‘physical health’&lt;/em&gt; while for NPGs it was &lt;em&gt;‘family’&lt;/em&gt;. In relation to other variables of interest examined in our study, PGs showed higher levels of functional impairments compared to NPG only in relation to overall &lt;em&gt;‘psychiatric distress’&lt;/em&gt; and severity of &lt;em&gt;‘insomnia’&lt;/em&gt; with no meaningful differences emerging in relation to &lt;em&gt;‘loneliness’&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;‘attention problems’&lt;/em&gt;, and severity of &lt;em&gt;‘headache experiences’&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The study findings support a holistic approach to GD diagnosis, considering functional impairments as a crucial factor. For clinicians and health professionals, understanding the specific areas of life affected by GD can enhance treatment efforts, ultimately improving the quality of life for those impacted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the realm of competitive esports, where the line between passion and compulsion can blur, the insights generate by our study not only contribute to our understanding of GD but also emphasize the critical role of industry-led initiatives in safeguarding the wellbeing of gamers. As we move forward, collaboration between researchers, health professionals, and industry stakeholders will be key in developing comprehensive strategies to address the challenges highlighted by this study.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let us continue this conversation and work together towards a healthier gaming community. Follow me on social media for real-time updates and discussions on the future of gaming and mental health. Together, we can navigate the challenges and opportunities presented by the digital age, ensuring that gaming remains a source of joy and innovation, not distress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34; id=&#34;heading&#34;&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stay tuned and follow me on &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://metalhead.club/@DrHalleyPontes&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Mastodon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/@DrHalleyPontes&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; for real-time updates on what&amp;rsquo;s happening next!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Speaking at the conference organised by the National Mental Health Programme of Slovenia (Nacionalni program duševnega zdravja)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/en/post/2023-11-p1/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/en/post/2023-11-p1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, I have delivered a keynote talk on Gaming Disorder to an interested audience of researchers, mental health practitioners, and government officials in Slovenia in the &amp;lsquo;National Conference on the Management of Non-Chemical Addictions&amp;rsquo; (Nacionalna Konferenca Obvladovanja Nekemičnih Zasvojenosti), organised in the context of Slovenia&amp;rsquo;s pioneering National Mental Health Programme (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.zadusevnozdravje.si&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;MIRA - Nacionalni program duševnega zdravja&lt;/a&gt;), which is supported by the National Institute of Public Health of Slovenia (&lt;a href=&#34;https://nijz.si&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Nacionalni Inštitut za javno zdravje)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a number of years now, Slovenia has been pioneering nation-wide research, prevention and treatment initiatives for behavioural addictions via its public health policies, mental health charities, and other public and private stakeholders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The conference was insightful as it provided an opportunity to discuss the issue of behavioural addictions and broader mental health with different experts from Slovenia. It is clear that public health and mental health need a multidisciplinary approach where there is transparency in the sharing of resources and information alongside an effort towards creating synergy between the different public and private organisations who are interested in nothing else but delivering mental health care to those in need.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The projects being currently developed in Slovenia are in my view leading and should serve as an example to many other countries interested in tackling the issue of behavioural addictions from an evidence-based perspective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A special thanks to Dr. Špela Selak, Mark Zmavc, Sanja Tkalec, and Tamara Arh who have all worked very hard to put up such an amazing conference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34; id=&#34;heading&#34;&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stay tuned and follow me on &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://metalhead.club/@DrHalleyPontes&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Mastodon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/@DrHalleyPontes&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; for real-time updates on what&amp;rsquo;s happening next!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Our second gaming research project and social responsibility campaign will soon be launched!</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/en/post/2023-09-p1/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/en/post/2023-09-p1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Hello everyone,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://esl.com/ggforall/smart-gaming&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;first successful independent research partnership with ESL Gaming&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; led by Prof. Christian Montag (University of Ulm, Germany) and I where we developed a pioneering social responsibility campaign aimed at understanding and mitigating disordered gaming harms in a large international gaming community, I am pleased to announce that our second research project and partnership with ESL Gaming will soon be launched.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Smart Gaming Project will follow the steps of our first project to allow us to further expand the knowledge we have built in the first project. As a result of the first project, we were able to publish several impactful research studies on various aspects of gaming behaviours in high-quality international journals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below I will briefly highlight my three favourite studies published out of the first project as they helped us:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.socscimed.2022.114721&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Understand how much time spent on gaming may be problematic in terms of gaming disorder&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. Specifically, we found that in a sample of 123,262 gamers from 168 countries, disordered gaming was associated with an average of weekly spent time gaming between 34.53 to 40.13 hours - depending on how gaming disorder is assessed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0261380&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Clarify the links between personality and gaming behaviours&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. In this particular study we analysed data from 50,925 gamers from 150 countries and we found that low conscientiousness and high neuroticism were strongly related to gaming disorder. We also found that personality traits were more strongly associated with gaming disorder than time spent gaming, which means that personality traits are critical to our understanding of disordered gaming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jpsychires.2023.06.003&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Shed light on the role of functional impairments in gaming disorder&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. Here, we used an initial sample of 192,260 gamers to analyse the data from those who 1) &lt;em&gt;met the diagnostic criteria for gaming disorder&lt;/em&gt; and 2) &lt;em&gt;that specified one area where gaming has negatively impacted them&lt;/em&gt;. We found that among these individuals (N = 2,162), the areas mostly affected by gaming-related functional impairments were school and/or work (50.69%), followed by psychological health (13.37%), and family-related functional impairments (12.26%). Conversely, the least affected area related to friends (4.67%). In sum, the most prominent gaming-related functional impairment experienced among disordered gamers was related to academic and/or professional activities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Needless to say that I have been extremely lucky to be involved in these studies and the project as a whole, so for that, I wish to thank my collaborators and ESL Gaming for the opportunity given to us to put research skills into good use so that we can develop knowledge able to help us understand the opportunities and pitfalls of gaming, to ultimately help those in need.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34; id=&#34;heading&#34;&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stay tuned and follow me on &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://metalhead.club/@DrHalleyPontes&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Mastodon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/@DrHalleyPontes&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; for real-time updates on what&amp;rsquo;s happening next!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Assessment of Gaming Disorder with the IGDS9-SF</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/en/post/2022-12-p2/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/en/post/2022-12-p2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Hello everyone,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was pleased to see that a recent study published by Anthony and colleagues (2022) in the journal &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1037/cps0000123&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Clinical Psychology: Science and Practice&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; provided further insights on the psychometric properties and usability of the &lt;strong&gt;Internet Disorder Scale-Short Form (IDS9-SF)&lt;/strong&gt;, which was the first brief standardized assessment tool for &amp;lsquo;Internet Gaming Disorder&amp;rsquo; as defined in the DSM-5.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The IGDS9-SF was published in December 2014 in the journal &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chb.2014.12.006&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Computers in Human Behavior&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, and after nearly a decade since its publication and numerous studies supporting its use worldwide, a new study provided further support to previous research.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Upon evaluating a set of 22 psychometric tests measuring &amp;lsquo;Internet Gaming Disorder&amp;rsquo;, Anthony and colleagues (2022) reported that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Among all reviewed measures, the IGDS9-SF has been evaluated by the highest number of empirical studies (n = 26). In contrast, all other measures were evaluated by only a few studies (ns = 1–5).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They further noted that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Based on the COSMIN guideline, the IGDS9-SF demonstrates sound structural validity, internal consistency reliability, construct validity (convergent and divergent validities), test-retest reliability, and measurement invariance among gender, age groups (including three studies evaluating measurement invariance between adolescent and adult samples), and regions with moderate- to high methodological quality.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Find out more about the IGDS9-SF and available documentation &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.halleypontes.com/tests/ids9-sf/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stay tuned and follow me on &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://metalhead.club/@DrHalleyPontes&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Mastodon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; for real-time updates on what&amp;rsquo;s happening!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Welcome to my new website!</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/en/post/2022-12-p1/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/en/post/2022-12-p1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Welcome aboard!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am really excited to release the new version of my website, which was developed using &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.r-project.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;R&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://gohugo.io/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Hugo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope we can keep connected and that I have enough time to keep you posted about my work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the meantime, I wish you all a truly awesome happy new year!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stay tuned and follow me on &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://metalhead.club/@DrHalleyPontes&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Mastodon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; for real-time updates on what&amp;rsquo;s happening!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
