<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Social Media Addiction | Dr. Halley Pontes</title>
    <link>http://localhost:4321/tags/social-media-addiction/</link>
      <atom:link href="http://localhost:4321/tags/social-media-addiction/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Social Media Addiction</description>
    <generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 01 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>http://localhost:4321/media/icon_hu3916292783086637300.png</url>
      <title>Social Media Addiction</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/tags/social-media-addiction/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Investigating the differential effects of social networking site addiction and Internet gaming disorder on psychological health</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/publication/2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/publication/2017/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Background and aims: Previous studies focused on examining the interrelationships between social
networking site (SNS) addiction and Internet gaming disorder (IGD) in isolation. Moreover, little
is known about the potential simultaneous differential effects of SNS addiction and IGD on psychological
health. This study investigated the interplay between these two technological addictions and ascertained
how they can uniquely and distinctively contribute to increasing psychiatric distress when accounting for
potential effects stemming from sociodemographic and technology-related variables. Methods: A sample of
509 adolescents (53.5% males) aged 10–18 years (mean = 13.02, SD = 1.64) were recruited. Results: It was
found that key demographic variables can play a distinct role in explaining SNS addiction and IGD. Furthermore,
it was found that SNS addiction and IGD can augment the symptoms of each other, and simultaneously contribute
to deterioration of overall psychological health in a similar fashion, further highlighting potentially common
etiological and clinical course between these two phenomena. Finally, the detrimental effects of IGD on psychological
health were found to be slightly more pronounced than those produced by SNS addiction, a finding that warrants
additional scientific scrutiny. Discussion and conclusion: The implications of these results are further discussed
in light of the existing evidence and debates regarding the status of technological addictions as primary and
secondary disorders.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
