<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>GDT | ZAN's Portfolio</title><link>https://sankethj.github.io/tags/gdt/</link><atom:link href="https://sankethj.github.io/tags/gdt/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>GDT</description><generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://sankethj.github.io/media/icon_hu_aeeeffb8443bfffd.png</url><title>GDT</title><link>https://sankethj.github.io/tags/gdt/</link></image><item><title>Assessing Internet Gaming Disorder - insights from our latest research</title><link>https://sankethj.github.io/post/2024-10-p2/</link><pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sankethj.github.io/post/2024-10-p2/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;In recent years, the conversation around Gaming Disorder has gained significant traction, especially as more people recognise
the impact of excessive gaming on mental health. In our &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.abrep.2024.100567" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;latest study&lt;/a&gt;, we took a closer look at two of the most widely used assessment
tools for GD: the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chb.2014.12.006" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Internet Gaming Disorder Scale–Short-Form (IGDS9-SF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; and
the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s11469-019-00088-z" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Gaming Disorder Test (GDT)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. Our goal was to evaluate how well these tools measure
disordered gaming and what that means for individuals and clinicians alike.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="what-is-gaming-disorder"&gt;What is Gaming Disorder?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.who.int/standards/classifications/frequently-asked-questions/gaming-disorder" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Gaming Disorder&lt;/a&gt; is a condition recognized in
the World Health Organisation&amp;rsquo;s International Classification of Diseases (ICD-11).
It involves a pattern of gaming behaviour where a person struggles to control their gaming habits, prioritises gaming over other
important activities and interests, and continues to play even when it leads to negative effects in their life.
Essentially, it means that gaming becomes more important than other aspects of daily living, which can harm a person&amp;rsquo;s wellbeing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="about-our-study"&gt;About our study&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For this study, we gathered a diverse group of 605 participants, all of whom were Spanish-speaking individuals aged between 16 and 73 years
who played video games at least once a week. Through an online survey, we assessed the reliability and effectiveness of the IGDS9-SF and GDT
in identifying symptoms of disordered gaming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using advanced statistical methods, we analysed the data to determine whether these two scales accurately measure a single underlying trait
(i.e., disordered gaming) and how well they can distinguish between different levels of severity. Accurately measuring Gaming Disorder is
crucial for identifying and treating individuals who may be struggling with excessive gaming and understanding the severity of their issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="our-key-findings"&gt;Our key findings&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of our most significant findings was that both the IGDS9-SF and GDT are unidimensional. This means that each scale effectively measures
one core aspect of Gaming Disorder. The results showed that the items (which represent the unique symptoms of Gaming Disorder) on both scales
work well together to reflect the same underlying issue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, both scales demonstrated high reliability, which means that they consistently provide accurate measurements of Gaming Disorder symptoms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also explored how well the items of each scale can differentiate between varying levels of Gaming Disorder. We found that the GDT performed
particularly well, achieving a strong scalability coefficient, which suggests that its items are effective at distinguishing between
individuals with different levels of gaming issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also found a clear hierarchy of item difficulty within both scales. For instance, in the IGDS9-SF, the most challenging item related
to the experience of &lt;strong&gt;negative consequences of gaming&lt;/strong&gt;, while the easiest item was about &lt;strong&gt;escapism&lt;/strong&gt;, which means that when assessing
Gaming Disorder, it is important to understand that the potential negative consequences resulting from excessive gaming is a much better
indicator of Gaming Disorder than playing video games excessively to escape real-life problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the GDT, the most difficult item involved &lt;strong&gt;experiencing significant life problems&lt;/strong&gt; due to gaming, which is highly consistent with the
findings of the IGDS9-SF. Interestingly, the easiest item was related to giving &lt;strong&gt;increased priority to gaming&lt;/strong&gt;, which is an important sign
of Gaming Disorder but certainly not as critical compared to the detrimental consequences excessive gaming can cause.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also found that &lt;strong&gt;withdrawal symptoms&lt;/strong&gt; (in IGDS9-SF) and &lt;strong&gt;experience of significant problems in life&lt;/strong&gt; (in GDT) were the most discriminative
items. This finding suggests that these two symptoms are particularly effective in differentiating individuals experiencing Gaming Disorder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="implications-of-our-findings"&gt;Implications of our findings&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The implications of our study are important for both individuals and mental health professionals. Firstly, it is important to pay attention
to more critical symptoms as these may require a greater level of intervention. One of the critical symptoms we identified relates to the
negative impact of excessive gaming on a person&amp;rsquo;s life (e.g., missing real-life opportunities, skipping school, missing work, etc).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secondly, the most discriminative items were: &lt;strong&gt;withdrawal symptoms&lt;/strong&gt; in the IGDS9-SF and the &lt;strong&gt;experience of significant life problems&lt;/strong&gt; in
the GDT. These two symptoms should be prioritised during assessments and clinicians should pay close attention to them as they appear to indicate
a more severe form of Gaming Disorder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, our findings suggest that the GDT may be slightly more effective than the IGDS9-SF in distinguishing between individuals with high
and low levels of Gaming Disorder, a finding that can help guide health practitioners in selecting the most appropriate assessment tool for their
clinical work with clients struggling with Gaming Disorder, ultimately leading to better targeted interventions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, our study supports the psychometric robustness of both the IGDS9-SF and GDT, confirming their utility in both research and
clinical settings for assessing Gaming Disorder. By utilising these tools, researchers and clinicians can better identify individuals at
risk for Gaming Disorder and implement more focussed interventions aimed at treating this condition and promoting healthier gaming behaviours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the conversation around gaming and mental health continues to evolve, our findings contribute to a growing body of evidence that can help
shape effective strategies for prevention and intervention in the realm of Gaming Disorder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="reference"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reference&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maldonado-Murciano, L., Pontes, H. M., Barrios, M., Gómez-Benito, J., &amp;amp; Guilera, G. (2024). Mokken scale analysis of the Internet Gaming Disorder
Scale–Short-Form and the Gaming Disorder Test. &lt;em&gt;Addictive Behaviors Reports&lt;/em&gt;, 100567. &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.abrep.2024.100567" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.abrep.2024.100567&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 style="text-align: justify;"&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stay tuned and follow me on &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://metalhead.club/@DrHalleyPontes" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Mastodon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://x.com/DrHalleyPontes" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;X (formerly Twitter)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; for real-time updates on what&amp;rsquo;s happening next!&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The Gaming Disorder Test (GDT)</title><link>https://sankethj.github.io/tests/gdt/</link><pubDate>Sat, 14 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sankethj.github.io/tests/gdt/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The GDT &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s11469-019-00088-z" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;(Pontes et al., 2021)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; is the first brief standardized psychometric tool
to assess Gaming Disorder (GD) in light of the current diagnostic criteria developed by World Health Organization in the latest
revision of the &lt;em&gt;International Classification of Diseases 11th Revision&lt;/em&gt; (ICD-11).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The GDT is a unidimensional tool comprising a total of 4 items measuring the clinical criteria for GD as in the ICD-11. The test was
originally developed in a cross-cultural study including a large sample of Chinese (47% male, mean age 19.22 years, SD = 1.57) and
British gamers (49.4% male, mean age 26.74 years, SD = 7.88) recruited online.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although the GDT has been developed in adult samples, several studies had success using the GDT in younger populations.
Specifically, &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jpsychires.2025.05.057" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;(Liang et al., 2025)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; used it in a sample of 201,906
children and adolescents aged 6–18 years old. Furthermore, the GDT is also due to be used in the large-scale research study
carried out by The Health Behaviour in School-aged Children (HBSC).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, the GDT has been extensively investigated at the psychometric level across several studies, with the results being satisfactory at
several psychometric levels, such as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Construct validity: (i) factorial validity; (ii) nomological validity, (iii) convergent validity; (iv) discriminant validity; and (v) concurrent validity. The GDT has also been shown to be reliable according to several indicators of internal consistency. The original &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s11469-019-00088-z" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;study&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; provides further information about the validity of the scale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A study by &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyt.2020.577366" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Wang and Cheng (2020)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; reported that the GDT presents with adequate reliability, structural validity, and criterion validity. In terms of measurement invariance, the GDT showed scalar invariance for gender, age, and employment status.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A review study conducted by &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/10731911211055435" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Karhulahti and colleagues (2021)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; reported that of all available assessment tools for GD, the GDT was the only tool to show the highest level of validity in the operationalization of the assessment criteria for GD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A meta-analysis study conducted by &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.abrep.2024.100563" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Jahrami and colleagues (2024)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; synthesized the existing psychometric data regarding the GDT globally by reviewing a total of 17 studies in 14 languages. The authors concluded that there is robust evidence supporting the GDT&amp;rsquo;s internal consistency across diverse populations and that the test has strong psychometric properties without risk of bias across all reviewed studies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The GDT can be used in time-limited research on GD and future studies using clinical samples, longitudinal, and cross-cultural designs are necessary to consolidate the initial findings obtained in the original study. Languages in which the test has been developed so far include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0279062" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Bengali &amp;#x1f1e7;&amp;#x1f1e9;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: Download &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://osf.io/vgj2t" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s11469-019-00088-z" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Chinese &amp;#x1f1e8;&amp;#x1f1f3;&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; Download &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://osf.io/gywa7" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ajp.2023.103638" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Study 2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s11469-025-01524-z" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Chinese &amp;#x1f1ed;&amp;#x1f1f0;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: Download &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://osf.io/ef2yu" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jpsychires.2024.05.023" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Czech &amp;#x1f1e8;&amp;#x1f1ff;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: Download &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://osf.io/ghuxb" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s11469-019-00088-z" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;English &amp;#x1f1ec;&amp;#x1f1e7;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: Download &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://osf.io/bz5ka" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.3390/jcm8101691" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;German &amp;#x1f1e9;&amp;#x1f1ea;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: Download &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://osf.io/uk5zn" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s12671-022-02066-4" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Italian &amp;#x1f1ee;&amp;#x1f1f9;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: Download &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://osf.io/udek3" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/01632787231185845" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Malay &amp;#x1f1f2;&amp;#x1f1fe;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: Download &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://osf.io/48wm5" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1186/s40359-023-01368-z" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Persian &amp;#x1f1ee;&amp;#x1f1f7;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: Contact the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:Amir.Pakpour@ju.se"&gt;author&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://http://cspsychiatr.cz/detail.php?stat=1386" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Polish &amp;#x1f1f5;&amp;#x1f1f1;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: Download &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://osf.io/sy8f7" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://cspsychiatr.cz/detail.php?stat=1386" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Slovak &amp;#x1f1f8;&amp;#x1f1f0;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: Download &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://osf.io/dnvrx" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s11469-021-00704-x" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Spanish &amp;#x1f1ea;&amp;#x1f1f8;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: Download &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://osf.io/ugwhe" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1111/sjop.13010" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Swedish &amp;#x1f1f8;&amp;#x1f1ea;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: Download &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://osf.io/fp36n" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1080/24732850.2024.2351091" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Thai &amp;#x1f1f9;&amp;#x1f1ed;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: Download &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://osf.io/vjpc8" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://hdl.handle.net/20.500.12416/4617" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Turkish &amp;#x1f1f9;&amp;#x1f1f7;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: Download &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://osf.io/cmp96" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://dusunenadamdergisi.org/article/1519" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Study 2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1186/s41155-024-00328-9" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Vietnamese &amp;#x1f1fb;&amp;#x1f1f3;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: Download &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://osf.io/7ajxz" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class="flex px-4 py-3 mb-6 rounded-md bg-primary-100 dark:bg-primary-900"&gt;
&lt;span class="pr-3 pt-1 text-primary-600 dark:text-primary-300"&gt;
&lt;svg height="24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" viewBox="0 0 24 24"&gt;&lt;path fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round" stroke-width="1.5" d="m11.25 11.25l.041-.02a.75.75 0 0 1 1.063.852l-.708 2.836a.75.75 0 0 0 1.063.853l.041-.021M21 12a9 9 0 1 1-18 0a9 9 0 0 1 18 0m-9-3.75h.008v.008H12z"/&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="dark:text-neutral-300"&gt;If you know of any other existing validation study and/or if you wish to further develop and validate the GDT in another language,
please do get in touch with me via &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:contactme@halleypontes.com"&gt;email&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description></item><item><title>The Gambling Disorder Test (GDT)</title><link>https://sankethj.github.io/tests/gdt2/</link><pubDate>Wed, 15 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sankethj.github.io/tests/gdt2/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The Gambling Disorder Test (GDT) &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1037/pas0001374" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;(Pontes et al., 2025)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; is a brief standardized
psychometric test designed to assess Gambling Disorder (GD code: 6C50) according to the most recent WHO diagnostic
framework proposed in the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://icd.who.int/browse/2025-01/mms/en" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;ICD-11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The development of the GDT marks a significant shift in how GD is assessed in light of recent scientific developments. This
is because most research on GD utilizes popular assessment tools that are highly problematic, such as the Problem Gambling Severity
Index (PGSI) &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.greo.ca/Modules/EvidenceCentre/files/Ferris%20et%20al%282001%29The_Canadian_Problem_Gambling_Index.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;(Ferris &amp;amp; Wynne, 2001)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;,
which does not reflect the current clinical and theoretical understanding of GD. Specifically, the PGSI was developed over 20 years
ago based on the DSM-IV which did not consider GD a behavioral addiction but an impulse-control disorder instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, the PGSI was developed in reference to the South Oaks Gambling Screen (SOGS) &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://psycnet.apa.org/doi/10.1176/ajp.144.9.1184" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;(Lesieur &amp;amp; Blume, 1987)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
which has its own significant limitations. More specifically, the SOGS was developed based on the DSM-III and has been reported
to produce high rates of false-positive diagnosis, overestimating the true number of affected individuals in the general
population &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://psycnet.apa.org/doi/10.1016/S0306-4603%2800%2900158-1" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;(Stinchfield, 2002)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To overcome these issues, the GDT was developed based on data from a large, nationally representative sample of adults
from the United Kingdom. The overall development process ensured that the final items were directly aligned with the four core
diagnostic features of GD as defined by the WHO, emphasizing its clinical relevance, as well as diagnostic, and conceptual alignment.
The GDT is a brief and cost-effective tool that can be freely used by clinicians to assist in the clinical assessment of GD and by
researchers conducting research on GD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the original psychometric development and validation study published in the prestigious refereed journal
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1037/pas0001374" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Psychological Assessment&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, the GDT has shown excellent psychometric properties in terms of:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Construct validity: (i) factorial validity; (ii) population cross-validity, and (iii) concurrent validity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Internal consistency: (i) Cronbach&amp;rsquo;s alpha; (ii) McDonald&amp;rsquo;s Omega; (iii) Composite Reliability; and (iv) Factor Determinacy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Measurement invariance: (i) Gender invariance (full scalar).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is important to note that further research, including, but not limited to, longitudinal and cross-cultural designs, are necessary
to expand the initial validation findings reported. At present, the GDT is available in the following languages:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1037/pas0001374" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;English &amp;#x1f1ec;&amp;#x1f1e7;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: Download &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://osf.io/exyua" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class="flex px-4 py-3 mb-6 rounded-md bg-primary-100 dark:bg-primary-900"&gt;
&lt;span class="pr-3 pt-1 text-primary-600 dark:text-primary-300"&gt;
&lt;svg height="24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" viewBox="0 0 24 24"&gt;&lt;path fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round" stroke-width="1.5" d="m11.25 11.25l.041-.02a.75.75 0 0 1 1.063.852l-.708 2.836a.75.75 0 0 0 1.063.853l.041-.021M21 12a9 9 0 1 1-18 0a9 9 0 0 1 18 0m-9-3.75h.008v.008H12z"/&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="dark:text-neutral-300"&gt;If you know of any other existing validation study and/or if you wish to further develop and validate the GDT in another language,
please do get in touch with me via &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:contactme@halleypontes.com"&gt;email&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>